<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here begynneth a lytell treatyse called the wyse chylde of thre yere olde The enfant sage beynge of thre yeres of age demaunded by Adryan emperoure. The whiche hym answered vnto euery thynge he asked.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1568</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18607</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109150</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844800</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844800</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9645</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18607)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9645)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 30:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here begynneth a lytell treatyse called the wyse chylde of thre yere olde The enfant sage beynge of thre yeres of age demaunded by Adryan emperoure. The whiche hym answered vnto euery thynge he asked.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In fletestrete at the sygne of the Sonne by Wynkyn de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted in london :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1568]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>With woodcut title vignette.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9645:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9645:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ Here begynneth a lytell treatyſe called the wyſe chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of thre yere olde. The enfant ſage beynge of thre yeres of age demaunded by Adryan Emperoure. The whiche hym anſwered vnto euery thynge he aſked.</head>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9645:2"/>
HEre foloweth the anſwers that the enfant ſage the whiche ne had but thre yeres of age and was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led lytell ſone vnto the emperour / and he was fyrſt reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnto an archebyſſhop. &amp; the ſayd archebyſſhope reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded hym vnto a patryarche of Iheruſalem. And the ſayd patryarche reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded hym vnto a duke ryght ſage ryght humble and the beſte vnderſtandynge hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that was in all the lande. And whan the chylde was comen in to the cyte where this ſage duke was he yode to ſpeke vnto hym. And than the knyghtes of that duke tolde hym. Here is the enfant ryght ſage. And than ſome hym ſalewed and ſayde vnto hym. Sage enfant frome what partyes arte thou comen. And the chylde anſwered I am comen frome my fader / and frome my moder / and was create of oure lorde Ieſu chryſt. And ſome other kny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghtes of the duke ſayde vnto him thou arte ſage. And the chylde anſwered hym that he is ſage the whiche is cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyſed by hym ſelfe. And all theſe thynges aboue ſayd we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re compted vnto the Emperour Adryan that than was at Rome / the whiche made hym to come vnto hym / and ſayd vnto hym in this wyſe. Sage enfant howe is the ſkye made. And the enfant anſwered hym in this maner yf hit had ben made by the hande of man it hadde fallen forth with / and yf it had be borne it hadde ben deed longe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme ſyth. Alſo the emperour demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded what god made fyrſte. And the chylde anſwered hym lyght and clerte at all tymes. ¶ Alſo the Emperour demaunded hym how a man maye vnderſtande that the trinite is one ſelfe god reygnynge in thre perſonnes. And the chylde anſwered hym by the ſonne in whom thou ſhalt fynde thre thynges That is to vnderſtonde ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / ſhynynge / and heate / the whiche be in ſeperables for the one ne maye be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other. Alſo the Emperour demaunded hym / who
<pb facs="tcp:9645:2"/>yede fyrſte oute frome the mouthe of oure lorde. And the chylde anſwered ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euangeliſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ſayd In principio erat verbum / et verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> erat apud deum. &amp;c. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded yf god created y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde inlytell of tyme. And the chylde hym anſwered / in a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell whyle as the openynge of an eye. for he create all the worlde in a momente but after by the ſpace of .vi. dayes he made the thynges beynge in the worlde. That is to vnderſtonde / the ſondaye he create the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gels. The mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daye he made the fyrmament. The tewelday he made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erthe / the ſee the froges / and the ſwete waters of the ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and fontaynes. The wenneſdaye he made the byr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and the lyſſhes of all maners. The thurſdaye he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the trees and the beeſtes of all manyers. The frydaye he made and formed Adam vnto his owne lykenes.</p>
            <p>The ſaturdaye he reſted hym / and bleſſed all that / that he hadde made and formed. Alſo the Emperour hym de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded what hope the marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes haue. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde anſwered hym lytell for that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they gette they porchaſe often by fraulde and deſceyte. Alſo the emperoure hym demaunded what ſayeſt thou of laberours. And the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de hym anſwered the mooſt grete parte of them ſhall be ſaued for they lyuen of the yre ſymplye. and the people of god ſeden of theyr trauayle. Alſo the emperour hym de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded what ſayeſt thou of theſe chyldren. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde hym anſwered that thoſe that deyen In the age of thre yeres and vnder and the whiche ben baptyſed ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. And the emperour hym demaunded. It is wryten y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our lorde Ieſu chryſt is deed for to agenbye the good and the euyll. And the chylde hym anſwered that Ieſu chryſt is deed for theſe ebryeux y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche weron than yll for they weren myſerrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. and alſo it is in ſcrypture that he is deed for all people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for by his dethe ſha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l be ſaued of all
<pb facs="tcp:9645:3"/>generacyons of people. Alſo the emperour hym demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in how many maners a man maye be ſaued, and the chylde hym anſwered in ſeuen / pryncypally fyrſt by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tym. Secondely by martyrdome. Thyrdely by confeſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and penaunce. Fourthly by terys wepynge. Fythely by almeſdedys. Syxtely by indulgences. That is to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtonde that we pardon with good harte and with good wyll thoſe the whiche haue myſoone vnto vs. The .vij. by the werkes of mercy. Alſo the emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded what the confeſſyon auaylleth. And the chylde hym anſwered that confeſſyon and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trycyon pourgeth all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres. Alſo the emperour hym demaunded what payne thoſe ſholde haue that be in this benefyces. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde anſwered y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhall peryſſhe with ſymon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enchantour. And thoſe that ſellen them ſhall be meſellys in the ſoule as teſſe. Alſo the emperour demaunded hym what payne the chyldren ſholde haue the whiche dye without baptyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. And the chylde anſwerde hym that they ſholde be in derkenes. And ſholde be put from the vyſyon of our lorde Ieſu chryſt / but a man ſholde not vnderſtonde in ſuche derkenes that they ne ſe clerely the clerte of heuen for that ſholde be payne / &amp; they ſhall haue no payne / but they ſhall be moore caſed than ony mortall man in this worlde. The emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded yf it were ſynne to take his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynne vnto wyfe or his goſſyp / or his filliole / or ony of his lygnage. And the chylde hym anſwered. it is no ſyn after nature / but it is after the ordynaunce of the chyrche as whan Adam ete the appell it was no ſynne but for that / that he treſpaſſed the commaundement of oure lorde and fauyour ieſu chryſt. And therfore was it a ryght greuous ſynne. Alſo the emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded wherfore was than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy faders taken theyr coſyns and parentes vnto wynes. And the chylde hym anſwered / for that that they
<pb facs="tcp:9645:3"/>heden than leue to loue theyr prochyns and nereſte of blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Alſo the emperour hym demaunded what ſayeſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> of knyghtes. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde anſwered I ſaye neyther yll ne good. The emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded where was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt woman create. And the chylde anſwered hym in paradis terreſtre of the ſyde of Adam. The emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded wherfore was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woman create of the ſyde of Adam. And he anſwered to the ende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were by dyleccion all of one hart and of one wyll. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded wheder thoſe ben happye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue theyr deſyres and wyll in this worlde. And he anſwered y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be not hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py / but thoſe ben happy the whiche god ne letteth to do theyr wylles and deſyres in this / but correeteth them by aduerſyte. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded what is ory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynall ſynne. and he anſwered it is faute of iuſtyee. Alſo he demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule ne myght growe. And the chylde anſwered no not in quantite / but in good vertu &amp; reaſon. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demaunded wherfore is it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome ben borne foles ſens that they haue a ſoule reaſonable. And he anſwered whan they ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyued of yll and groſe humours in the wome of theyr moder ſome what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule is greued for the ylle dyſpoſycyon of the body. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour demaunded hym whiche is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynge mooſt cruell vnto the poore or vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryche / and he anſwered hym the dethe. Alſo the emperour him demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded what thynge is man. And he anſwered that it is ymagenynge of our lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Ieſu chriſt. Alſo the emperour hym demaunded what thynge is woman. And he ſayd / it is the ymagenynge of dethe. Alſo the emperour hym demaunded at what hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ete Adam of the fruyte that our lorde hym had defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And he anſwered at the thyrde houre. and at the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of none he was caſte oute of paradyſe. Alſo the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour hym demaunded what thynge is it wherof a man
<pb facs="tcp:9645:4"/>maye neuer fede hym ynough / and the chylde anſwered that it is of gayne / or wynnynge. And the emperour him demaunded how many ſynnes ben there the whiche ne ben pardonned in this worlde ne in lyke wyſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other. And the enfant hym aniſhered twayne. The fyrſt is who ſo that byleueth not in the reſurrece you of our lorde Ieſu chryſt. The ceconde is who ſo deſpeyreth hym of the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of god. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demaunded what thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge is beſt or worſte / and the chylde hym anſwered that it was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demaunded by how many maners a man dyeth. and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde hym anſwered by .v. The fyrſt is by pouerte. The .ij. by ignoraunce the .iij. is by pyte. The iiij. is by drede. The .v. is by iniquite. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demaunded how many langages ben there in the worlde. &amp; the chyld hym anſwerde there are .lxxii. Alſo the empereur hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded how many maner of ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ben there in the worlde. &amp; the chylde an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there were .xxiiij. Alſo the emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded what was he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche put name vnto all the beeſtes / &amp; he anſwered that dyd Adam. Alſo the emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſte thynge of all the worlde. and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde hym anſwered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man whan the ſoule is oute. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour him demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded whiche is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt lyght thynge of all the worlde. &amp; the chylde an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thought. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded what thynge is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſkye. &amp; the chylde anſwered that it is a lyght of clerte diuine. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demaunded / what ſuſteyneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erthe. &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde anſwered y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demaunded / what ſuſtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water. and the chylde anwerede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the .iiii. euange liſtes. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> empereur hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded / what ſuſteyneth the .iiij. euangeliſles. &amp; the chylde anſwered / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpyrytuell fyre. Alſo the emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded what ſuſteyneth
<pb facs="tcp:9645:4"/>the ſpyrytuell fyre. &amp; the chylde anſwered a tree y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche was planted in paradſe in the begynnynge whan god came in to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> vyrgyn mary. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded who was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſte hermyte. and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde anſwered y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was ſaynt poll. Alſo the emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded / what thynge is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neuer may be nor neuer ſhall be. and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde anſwered that / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> valde of gelboe. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded who made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt chyrche / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dyd ſaynt pol. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour him demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded / what was he the whiche faſted thre dayes and thre nyghtes / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde anſwered hym that was Ionas in the whales wombe. Alſo the emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded how many of yeres had noe whan he began to make the arche. &amp; the chylde anſwered hym fyue hondreth of yeres Alſo the emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded / in how many yeres was the ſayd arche made / and the chylde anſwered in a hondreth yeres. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demaunded / how many dayes the arche was on the water. &amp; the chylde an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered / that it was theron fortye dayes. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded / how longe / how large / and how hye the ſayd arche was / and the chylde hym anſwered that hit had .CCC. fadome in lengthe .CCxxx. of heyght / and a .Clx. in largenes. Alſo that emperour him demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded / In what place is the ſayd arche now / &amp; the chylde anſwered hym that hit is vpon a hye mountayne in armenie that men call Archenclyn. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demaunded what was he that planted &amp; ſette fyrſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyne. &amp; the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de anſwered hym that it was noe. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. who made the fyrſt cyte. &amp; the chylde him an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that it was zurie. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded / what was he the whiche demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the mooſt grete gyfte that euer man demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded / and the chylde anſwered that / that dyde Ioſeph of armathye the whiche demaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:9645:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9645:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9645:6"/>our lorde Ieſu chryſt beynge on the croſſe whome he put in the ſepulcre. Alſo the emperour hym demaunded / wherfore is it that men ſholde ſonner faſte on the frydaye than theſe other dayes. And the chylde anſwered hym. For .viij. reaſons pryncypally. The fyrſte is for that that on the frydaye our lorde Ieſu chryſt formed Adam. The ſeconde for that / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> on the fryday ſaynt Iohu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bapteſt bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſed our lorde in the flome iordayn. The thirde is for that that on the fryday Dauid y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophete ſlewe the grete go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyas. The .iiij. is for that / that on the frydaye oure lorde toke humayne fleſſhe in the wombe of the gloryouſe vyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen marye. The .v. is for that / that the frydaye ſaynt ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the fyrſt martyr was ſtoned. The .vi. for that / that on the frydaye ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bapteſt was beheded. The .vij. for on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frydaye our lorde Ieſu chryſt was crucified. The viij. for that / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frydaye our lorde Ieſu chryſt ſhall deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cende from heuen for to holde his Iugement in the vale of Ioſepath. Alſo the Emperoure hym demaunded in how many maners a man maye be dampned / and the chylde hym anſwered / in .iiij. maners pryncypally.</p>
            <p>The fyrſte is by neglygence. The ſeconde is by anger of tre and to ſhewe openly his ſynnes. The thyrde is of the doubte of the payne that a man hathe to amende hymſelf The .iiij. is of ylle thynge to be euermore in ſynne. Alſo the emperour hym demaunded / what thynges they ben the whiche beſte pleaſeth vnto our lorde Ieſu chryſt. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde anſwered / thre thynges pryncypally. The fyrſt is too do trewe penaunce of his ſynnes. The ſeconde is largeſſe and pacyence in pouerte. The thyrde is abſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of ſynne. Alſo the emperour hym demaunded what thynge is that the whiche mooſt dyſpleaſed vnto man. And the chylde ſayd it is lyfe of his enemyes and noyſant Alſo this emperour hym demaunded / how many ſonnes
<pb facs="tcp:9645:6"/>and doughters hade Adam / &amp; the chylde ſayd .xxx. ſonnes and .xxx. doughters without cam abell nor ſeph. Alſo the emperour hym demaunded who was the fyrſt that ſange maſſe. And the chylde anſwerde hym that is was melche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedech. Alſo the emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded who was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt thefe. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde hym anſwerde that it was Seph the fyrſte ſone of Adam. Alſo the emperour hym demaunded what was he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> was borne before his fader &amp; bygoten befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re his moder the .iiij. of the worlde he ſlewe and had had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maydenhede of his grande moder. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde anſwerde that it was Cayn / for his fader and his moder that is to vnderſtonde Adam and Eue were create and alſo he ſlewe his broder Abel / for they ne were than but .iiij. in the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and had the maydenhede of his grande dame the erthe that labourede it. Alſo the emperoure hym demaunded what was he that entrede fyrſte in to paradys. And the chylde anſwered that it was the good thefe whome god pardonned on the croſſe. Alſo the emperour hym demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded whiche were the mooſt noble weddynges that euer were. And the chylde hym anſwered that was the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynges of Archideclin where god chaunged the water in to wyne / and there were our lorde and the vyrgyn marye. Alſo the emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded who be thoſe that ſhall neuer deye tyll vnto the ende of the worlde. And the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de anſwerde hym that it was Enoch and Helie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ben in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yate of paradys terreſtre holdynge euery of them a ſworde brennynge in theyr mouthes. Alſo the emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded what was he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deſpoyled his moder. &amp; the chylde anſwerde hym that it was Adam whan he began to laboure the erthe. Alſo the emperour hym demaunded what thynge is it of the ſee and the chylde anſwered that it is awaye in certayne and merueyllous. Alſo the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour hym demaunded what thynge is that as the dethe.
<pb facs="tcp:9645:7"/>and the chylde ſayd that it is a thynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ne maye fynyſſhe ne entre. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded what was he that dyed two tymes. &amp; the chylde hym anſwered that it was lazar the broder of marye magdaleyne and of marie marche the whiche god areyſed. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperoure hym demaunded of howe many thynges was man for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. and the chylde hym anſwered of ſyxe thynges pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cypally. That is to vnderſtonde the fieſſhe made is of the ſlyme of the erthe. The blode is made of the water of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſee. The bones were made of the ſtones the brethe was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of the wynde. The eyes were mage of the ſone. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule was treated of the holy ghoſt. Alſo the emperoure hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by what manere bryngeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl a man in to helie. And the chylde hym anſwered remembre the that euen in lyke wyſe as by baptym is pardoned theory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynall ſynne. Alſo in lyke wyſe by confeſſyon and penaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce ben pardonne all that other ſynnes. Alſo the emperour hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded is ordeyned vnto man y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> terme of his deth or of his lyfe / and the chylde hym anſwered that god all had ordeyned for oure ſaluacyon. Alſo the emperour hym demaunded in whome byleueſte thou. And he anſwered In god almyghty. That is to vnderſtonde in the father and in the ſone and in the holy ghoſt the whiche ben thre parſones in one eſſence and in one holy trinite. Alſo the emperour hym demaunded byleueſt thou y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu chryſt ſhadowed hym in the wombe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hloryous vyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyn Marye and that he was borne of her very god &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, and the chylde anſwered that yes and I byleue that he hathe ſuffred honger and thorſte and other try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulacyons for to agayne bye vs ſynners. And I byleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at the daye of aſſencyon he mounted in to heuen. And that on whyght ſondaye he ſent his holy eſpirite vnto his dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyples and that he ſhall come vppon the erthe to holde
<pb facs="tcp:9645:7"/>his Iugement / and that vnto the good he ſhall gyue lyfe and glorye in his paradis by all tymes and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ylle he ſhall ſende in to helle frome whens they ſhall neuer departe. Alſo the emperour hym demaunded where our lorde hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de hym before that he created the worlde. And the chylde hym anſwered that he was in a wodde there where he made fagotes for to bourne the and all theſe the whiche wyll from henſforth enquere of the ſecretes of our lorde in whome there ne is begynnynge nor endynge.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprynted in london in Fleteſtrete at the ſygne of the Sonne by wynkynde worde</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9645:8"/>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>sun and stars, representing the sign of the Sun</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>W <figure>
                        <figDesc>47</figDesc>
                     </figure> C</p>
                  <p>Wynkyn de worde.</p>
                  <figDesc>Caxton's printer's device, appropriated by Wynkyn de Worde</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9645:8"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
